今は ユダヤ人の暦では ティシュリ
It was now Tishri, the start of a month-long festival.
この月にさまざまな祭りが行われます
We had just rebuilt the wall of Jehovah’s great city.
エルサレムの城壁の修復は
完了したばかりです
Now it was time to rebuild
しかし今度は エホバとの関係を
修復しなければなりません
the spirituality of his chosen people.
神の律法を知らない人が大勢います
Many did not know God’s Law.
誰が教えますか
Who better to help us gain understanding
人々から尊敬されており
私より長くここにいる エズラです
than a man who had come before me—Ezra?
. . . the regulations and judicial decisions of Jehovah.
これがエホバの規定と法規です
エズラと他のレビ族は
He and other Levites read aloud
モーセの律法の書を読み聞かせました
from the Law of Moses.
They not only read it but they explained it,
ただ朗読するだけではなく
分かりやすく説明して
意味を教えたのです
putting meaning into it.
民は これまでの行いが
どれほど神を悲しませたかを
As a people, we began to understand
理解するようになりました
how badly we had disappointed Jehovah
安息日を守らないこと
by working on the Sabbath,
足が不自由な動物の犠牲を捧げること
offering lame sacrifices,
妻を離婚して他の民族の女性と
結婚することなどです
and divorcing our wives to marry foreign women.
It hurt our hearts, but by reading God’s Law,
心が痛みましたが
神の律法を聞いて学び
エホバへの崇拝が
どういうものかが分かりました
we were learning to be Jehovah’s people again.
Do not mourn or weep.
悲しんだり泣いたりしないでください
Now that you know what displeases God,
何がエホバを悲しませるかが分かった今
you can do what pleases him.
エホバの喜ぶことを行いましょう
行って 良い物を食べ
ぶどう酒を飲み
So go.
Eat the choice things, and drink what is sweet,
and send a portion to those who have nothing.
持っていない人と分け合いましょう
And do not feel sad,
悲しんではいけません
for the joy of Jehovah is your stronghold.
エホバからの喜びは
皆さんの力となるのです
We followed Jehovah’s instructions
私たちは仮小屋の祭りについての
エホバの指示に従いました
to observe the Festival of Booths.
We spent days rejoicing and giving thanks
神の祝福に感謝する
喜ばしい日々を過ごしました
for Jehovah’s blessing.
Then on the 24th day,
その月の24日には
we assembled to read God’s Law,
神の律法を聞くために集まり
to confess our sins,
罪を告白し
悪い行いについて泣き悲しみました
and to weep over our wrongdoing.
そして 書面で厳粛な誓約をしました
We made a binding agreement in writing.
私たちは エホバの律法に従うことを
心に決めたのです
We resolved to obey Jehovah’s Law.
Amen!
アーメン！アーメン！
でもすぐにそれを忘れた人もいました
But some soon forgot their promise.
Peleth!
ペレト！
Reham,
ラハム
here’s our rent payment.
今月の家賃分だ
Put them in a bag.
袋に入れろよ 運びにくいだろ
The basket is hard to carry.
Did you hear about Nehemiah’s latest idea?
ネヘミヤが言ったこと聞いたか？
You mean the plan to repopulate Jerusalem?
エルサレムに住むって話？
ああ くじで選ばれた家族が
移住させられる
I mean his ridiculous proposal to force families
to move into the city—1 out of 10 by lot.
ばかげた話だ
ああ 聞いてる
Yes, I heard.
うちが選ばれたんだ
And I had to be one who was chosen.
Why me?
どうしてだ？俺は地主だぞ
おかしいだろ
Doesn’t he care what this does to landholders like me?
Oh!
へえ！
So when are you supposed to move?
それでいつ引っ越すの？
引っ越す？俺は行かないぞ
Move?
I’m not moving anywhere.
好きな所に住む権利がある そうだろ
I have a right to live where I choose, and so do you.
うちは選ばれなかった
I wasn’t selected.
Not yet, you mean.
分かんないぞ
選ばれたら おまえも断るんだ
And when you are,
I need you to join me in refusing to move.
Raham,
ラハム
the king sent Nehemiah here to rebuild the city.
ネヘミヤは王の指示で
再建のために来た
Nehemiah is the governor.
ネヘミヤは総督だぞ
どうせ総督は代わる
ネヘミヤはシュシャンに帰る
Governors come, governors go.
The king is waiting for Nehemiah to return,
あいつがいなくなれば
また好きなようにできる
and when he does, things will get back to normal.
Even when Nehemiah goes back,
たとえネヘミヤがいなくなっても
エホバは見ておられる
Jehovah will still be here.
It is his will that Jerusalem be rebuilt.
エルサレムの再建はエホバの指示だ
Don’t you believe that?
信じてないのか？
So you would go along with Nehemiah?
ネヘミヤの肩ばかり持ちやがって
俺はどうなるんだ
How can you be so ungrateful?
Raham,
ラハム
your rent!
忘れ物
What was that all about?
何話してたの？
ラハムはエルサレムに
引っ越すのを嫌がってる
Raham refuses to move into Jerusalem,
僕にも行くなと
and he wants us to support him.
あなたは何て言ったの？
What did you say?
I told him Nehemiah is doing Jehovah’s will.
ネヘミヤはエホバに
従ってるって言ったんだ
Raham doesn’t understand how happy
エホバに従えば幸せになれるのに
he could be if-if he would just follow Jehovah’s direction.
ラハムはそれが分かってない
So we will move if we are selected?
うちも 選ばれたら引っ越すの？
Yes.
ああ
ネヘミヤに倣いたい
I’d rather be like Nehemiah than like Raham.
ラハムじゃなくて いいよね？
You agree?
ええ
Yes.
Me too.
いいよ
At the inauguration of the walls,
城壁の奉献式の日
エルサレムは神への感謝と
賛美の歌であふれました
we filled Jerusalem with songs of praise
and thanksgiving to God.
喜びの声ははるか遠くにまで
響き渡りました
Our great joy could be heard from far away.
シュシャンに戻ってからも
この時のことをよく思い返しました
When I finally returned to the king,
I thought about that day often.
でも まだエルサレムを
離れるべきではなかったのです
With what I know now, I wish I had never left.
エホバは 私が去った後
Jehovah raised up a messenger
who chronicled the things that happened
エルサレムで起きた事を
記録させるため
in Jerusalem during my absence.
ある人物を用います
His name was Malachi.
それはマラキです
トビヤを覚えていますか
Tobiah,
despite not being a Jew,
彼はユダヤ人ではありませんでしたが
still found his way into the temple.
神殿に出入りし
ユダヤ人との姻戚関係を利用して
He utilized his Jewish family ties
自分勝手に行動していました
to take advantage of the other Jews.
ここに来るのは久しぶりだな
どうした？
What brings you to the temple?
It’s been some time.
あなたにお会いしたくて
I just wanted to see you,
oh, and to bring you this small gift.
ああこれ つまらないものですが
トビヤ いつもすまないね
Tobiah, you are always so generous.
とんでもありません
It’s nothing, really.
ああ 今日は何かな？
Umm, is there nothing I can do for you?
Well, since you asked,
じゃあ1つ頼んでもいいですか
there’s one little thing you could do.
もちろん 何だい？
Tell me. What can I do for you?
ええっと 家族のことなんですが・・・
Well, speaking of family . . .
ああ
When our relatives, yours and mine, I mean,
私とあなたの親族が
サマリアから訪ねて来たとき
visit from Samaria, it would be so nice
一緒に食事できる場所が
あればいいと思って
to have a place to eat with them.
うーん
You know, right here in the temple, that is.
そう この神殿の中に
After all, they worship Jehovah too—often.
そしたら彼らもしょっちゅう
エホバを崇拝できますよね
OK, well, sometimes.
いや まあ 時々かな
A room in the temple?
神殿の中に？
But you know I can’t do that.
無理なのは知ってるだろ
That is, all the rooms are in use.
それに 空き部屋もない
All of them?
空き部屋がない？貯蔵室は？
Aren’t some of them just storerooms?
そこはレビ族の食糧置き場だ
But those are provisions for the Levites.
But can’t you clear one out for me? just one?
1つくらい使わせてくださいよ
1部屋 1部屋だけ
I only need one.
But what will Nehemiah say?
ネヘミヤが何と言うか
What difference does it make?
何を恐れているんですか
Nehemiah is far away in Shushan.
ネヘミヤはシュシャンですよ
But what if he finds out?
でも万が一
Who is going to tell him?
告げ口する人がいるんですか
まさかあなたが？
Are you going to tell him?
いや そんな！
No, no!
Then why worry?
なら 問題はない
So once again our high priest has given in to Tobiah.
大祭司はまたトビヤの言いなりか
どこに置けばいいですか
Where should I put this grain?
There’s room here.
ここに 気を付けて
Be careful! I’ve got it.
はーい
Look who’s coming.
見ろ 来たぞ
Can you hurry, please?
早くしてください
Once they get out of our way, let’s, uh,
物がなくなったら
テーブルを・・・ここに
let’s set the table here and then the chairs
そして椅子は
壁沿いに置いてください
kind of along the wall.
Tobiah, tell me, please,
トビヤ ここにあったものは
どこに持っていけばいいですか？
where should we store our provisions now?
知りませんよ 好きにすればいいでしょ
Wherever you want.
That’s your problem.
Now move along,
とにかく さっさとどいてください
like now, please.
All right, so we’ll unload here,
で・・・ 椅子はここでいいと
テーブルはこんなふうに・・・
and then like I said, chairs there, table here.
そして食糧はこの辺りに
置いていただけますか
エルヤシブは何を考えているんだ
How could Eliashib let anyone,
個人的な目的で部屋を
使ってはいけないはずだ
let alone a man like Tobiah,
ましてトビヤはユダヤ人でもない
take over a room for his own use
after all that Nehemiah did
せっかくネヘミヤが神殿を
神聖なものとしてくれたのに
to preserve the sacredness of the temple?
Most people don’t give tithes anymore anyway.
レビ族のための寄付も
ほとんどされていない
畑や羊の世話をしないと
食べていけないし
If we want to eat,
we need to go tend our own flocks and fields.
エホバに仕えてる意味が分かんない
It’s of no value to serve God.
Wait, brothers!
兄弟たち
We can’t let their wrong acts take away our joy.
喜びを失うべきじゃない
Why not?
エホバへの奉仕だけで
食べていけないんですよ
How have we benefited from serving Jehovah?
Yes. And doesn’t the scripture say:
それに 自分の「羊をよく
世話しなさい」って書いてある
“Take good care of your sheep”?
It also says:
でも 「忠実な人は多くの
祝福を受け［る］」とも書いてある
“A faithful man will receive many blessings.”
We must wait on Jehovah.
エホバを待たなきゃ
In time, he will straighten everything out.
いずれエホバが全てを正してくださる
Malachi saw how far the people had fallen.
マラキは人々がエホバを
軽んじているのを見ました
The Levites,
かつては律法を守ることを
誇りにしていたレビ族までが
once the proud keepers of Jehovah’s standards,
now found themselves questioning
今では自分たちの奉仕に
疑問を抱いています
the value of their own service.
Young man!
お兄さん！
羊持っていかない？
Why not offer a sheep?
供え物が大きいと 祝福も大きいよ
The bigger the offering,
the bigger the blessings.
それに ご近所にもいい顔ができる
And besides,
you know it’s more impressive to the neighbors, huh?
Thank you. I already have an offering.
大丈夫 もうありますから
Yes, yes, but look!
待って 待って
そう お兄さんいい人そうだから
You seem like a nice man.
So today, for you, a special price—huh?—
特別にお安くしとくよ
hardly more than you paid for these doves.
ああ このハトより安いくらい
ちょっと見ていきなって
Come take a look.
That sheep is blind!
その羊は目が見えてない
歩き方も変だ
And look at how it walks!
いやいや この品種ではこれが普通だよ
Young man, that’s absolutely normal for this breed.
God’s Law says not to offer blind, lame, or sick animals.
律法には欠陥のある動物を
捧げてはいけないと書いてある
もし羊を買えるんだったら
傷のないものにするさ！
If ever I can afford to offer a sheep, it’ll be a sound one.
お買い得なのに
品物もいいし 値段もいい
Don’t waste your money!
She’s a fine sheep at a fine price.
もういいから
I have to go.
Be practical!
賢くいこうよ！
そんなの ただの伝統だろ
Besides, it’s only a tradition.
Bah!
ああ！
神殿は変わってしまった
Temple services are not the same.
エホバのことなんて みんな考えてない
It’s as if they don’t even think about Jehovah.
Azubah!
アズバ！
What’s wrong?
どうした？
何があった？
Azubah, what happened?
ラハムは？
How’s Raham?
A certificate of divorce?
離婚証書？！
私 いい妻でいるように頑張ったわ
I tried to be a good wife,
but it wasn’t enough.
でも駄目だったみたい
Raham sent me away.
家を追い出された
Don’t fear, Azubah.
大丈夫だ アズバ
ここにいればいい 一緒に
You can live here with us.
We can all share.
そうよ
ああもう 私のせいだわ
Oh, God!
It’s all my fault.
You mustn’t think that way.
そんなふうに考えないで
But I didn’t give him children.
あの人の子を産めなかったから
With or without children,
結婚の絆に
子供がいるいないは関係ない
marriage is sacred.
Trust in Jehovah.
エホバを信じて
絶対に見捨てられない
He will never send you away.
ありがとう
Thank you.
ラハム！
Raham!
We had a visitor last night.
昨日 うちに誰が来たと思う？
It was your wife,
君の妻
いや「元」妻と言った方がいいのかな
or should I say your former wife.
Raham,
don’t you care how you’ve hurt your innocent mate?
何の落ち度もないのに
離婚するなんてひどいじゃないか
How can you be so hard-hearted?
Look! Moses said if you find something
モーセも言っただろ
妻に恥ずべき点があれば
indecent with your wife, a man must write
離婚証書を手渡し
家から去らせろって
a certificate of divorce, hand it to her,
and dismiss her.
If giving me no children isn’t indecent, then what is?
俺の子を産まなかったのは
立派な理由になる
Besides, I’m tired of living with her.
それにもうあいつには飽きたんだ
今日ギズラと結婚する
I’m marrying Gizla today.
Gizla?
ギズラ？
That Moabite girl?
モアブ人の？
I heard you bind yourself with an oath and a curse
ほかの民族の女性と
結婚しないって誓ったよね？
not to take a wife from the nations!
律法にはこうある
God’s Law says: “They will turn your sons away
「彼らはあなたの息子を
ほかの神々に仕えさせる・・・
“from following me to serve other gods;
then Jehovah’s anger will blaze against you”!
その時エホバの怒りが燃え」るって！
Who are you to counsel me?
俺に意見するつもりか？
Every man must find his own joy,
自分の幸せは自分で決める
and I intend to find mine.
ラハム 人を幸せにできるのは
エホバだけだ
Raham, only Jehovah can give true joy.
Do you really think you can give
自分の力で幸せになれるって
本気で思ってるのか
yourself more joy than he can?
エホバ どうしてですか
Jehovah,
why do we treat each other so treacherously,
私たちが互いに裏切り
profaning your covenant?
契約を汚しているのは
Malachi!
マラキ！
私の名を軽んじている
祭司たちに言いなさい
Say to the priests who are despising my name:
「子は父を敬い 召し使いは主人を敬う
“A son honors a father, and a servant his master.
私が父であるのなら
“So if I am a father, where is the honor due me?
私への敬意はどこにあるのか
And if I am a master, where is the fear due me?”
私が主人であるのなら
私への畏れはどこにあるのか」
いらっしゃい
My good man!
供え物はいかがですか おっ！
My good man, I see you have no offering.
Why have you Levites despised Jehovah’s name?
なぜレビ族はエホバの名を
軽んじているんだ
軽んじている？どういうことだ？
Despised it?
How?
You present a blind, lame, or sick animal
あなた方は
欠陥のある動物を捧げながら
as a sacrifice and say that it is nothing bad.
悪いことではないと言っている
エホバは受け入れられるだろうか？
Should Jehovah accept it from your hand?
肉になってしまえば
傷物かどうかなんて分からないさ
Once the meat is in our pot,
no one can tell if it was lame or sound.
そうか エホバにも
分からないと思うか？
What about Jehovah? Can he tell the difference?
One day Jehovah will come to his temple.
いつの日かエホバが神殿に来て
He will cleanse you sons of Levi by fire.
金や銀のようにあなた方を
精錬するでしょう
マラキ いいかげんにしろ
Malachi, what’s gotten into you?
みんなが受け入れていることに
言い掛かりをつけるな
Why should you complain
when everyone else approves?
エホバは言われました
“‘O priests, if you refuse to take it to heart,’
「祭司たちよ あなたたちが
心に留めないなら
“says Jehovah,
“‘I will send on you the curse,
私はあなたたちに災いをもたらし
“‘and I will turn your blessings into curses.
あなたたちの祝福を災いに変える
私のもとに戻ってきなさい
Return to me, and I will return to you,’ says Jehovah.”
そうすれば 私も
あなたたちのもとに戻ろう」
戻るとはどういうことですか
How are we supposed to return?
「神から奪うことなど
あり得ないと思うか
“‘Will a mere human rob God?
あなたたちは奪っている」と
エホバは言われました
“But you are robbing me,’ says Jehovah.
奪っている？
How have we robbed him?
“‘In the tithes and in the contributions.
「10分の1や寄進物のことである」
“‘You are robbing me—yes,
「国民全体が私から奪っている
“the entire nation is,’ says Jehovah.
“‘Bring the entire tithe into the storehouse,
10分の1全部を持ってきて
私の家に食物があるようにしなさい
“‘so there may be food in my house;
“‘and test me out, please,
私が天の水門を開いて
“‘and see whether I will not open to you
あふれるほどに祝福を注ぐかどうか
“‘the floodgates of the heavens
私を試してほしい」とも言われました
“‘and pour out on you a blessing
until there is nothing lacking.’”
And there’s another thing you do
それに 神が犠牲を受け入れられない
ほかの理由もあります
so that he no longer looks favorably
on anything you offer.
それは何だ？
Why not?
Because you betray the wife of your youth,
あなた方は若い時からの
妻を裏切っています
although she’s your partner, your legal wife.
しかし そうしない人もいました
There are some who don’t do that
聖なる力が残っていたからです
because they have what remains of the spirit.
自分の内面の傾向に気を付けなさい
So guard yourselves respecting your spirit,
and do not deal treacherously
若い時からの妻を裏切ってはいけません
with the wife of your youth.
「私は離婚を憎む」と
エホバは言われました
“‘For I hate divorce,’ says Jehovah the God of Israel.”
The lips of a priest should safeguard knowledge,
祭司の唇は知識を保つべきであり
民は祭司の口に律法を求めるべきです
and people should seek the law from his mouth.
なのに あなた方は多くの人の
信仰を妨げています
But you,
you have made many stumble.
マラキに与えられたエホバの言葉は
Jehovah’s message revealed that the problem
was in their hearts.
問題が人々の心にあることを
明らかにしました
In spite of that,
それでもマラキは 正しいことを
行いたいと思う人たちを探しました
Malachi sought out those who found joy
in doing what was right.
ペレト
Peleth.
Malachi.
マラキ
How are you?
アズバ 元気を出してください
Azubah,
don’t despair.
You will see the distinction
皆さんは正しい人と悪い人
between the righteous and the wicked,
神に仕える人と仕えない人の
違いを目にすることになります
between one who serves God
and one who doesn’t.
さすが 預言者だわ
You must be a prophet.
I serve Jehovah as you do.
あなたと同じエホバの奉仕者です
And I can tell you that when you speak with one another
皆さんがエホバについて語り合う時
about Jehovah, he pays attention.
エホバは耳を傾けておられます
A book is written before him of those
神は ご自分を畏れる人たちのことを
who fear him and meditate on his name.
記録の書に記されます
エホバが共におられますように
May Jehovah be with you.
私は何年もエルサレムを離れていました
For years, I was away from Jerusalem,
でもそこの人たちのことは
忘れませんでした
but my heart was always with my people.
それで王からエルサレムに
戻る許可をもらいます
I requested to return to them.
でも戻ってきて 衝撃を受けました
But what I found shocked me.
エルヤシブ！
Eliashib!
あなたに平和がありますように
May you have peace.
ネヘミヤ！
Nehemiah!
I wasn’t expecting . . .
ど どうしてここに・・・？
レビ族と歌い手たちはどこですか
Where are all the Levites and the singers?
Some of them are away right now.
ちょっと出掛けてて・・・
出掛けてる？ どういうことですか
Away?
Why are they away?
ああ・・・ あっ ペダヤ ペダヤ！
Pedaiah is here!
Pedaiah,
show Governor Nehemiah around.
ネヘミヤをご案内して
ああ ちょっと失礼していいですか
Excuse me, please.
ああどうぞ
Of course.
Pedaiah,
ペダヤ 神殿での奉仕はどうですか
tell me about the temple services.
Do you have all the provisions that you need?
食糧は足りていますか
Governor Nehemiah,
ほとんどありません
we have nearly no provisions at all.
どういうことですか？
How can that be?
For a long time, the priests and the Levites
長いこと祭司とレビ族は
務めを果たしていません
have not taken their duties seriously.
When the people saw that,
それを見て人々は10分の1を
納めなくなりました
they stopped bringing in tithes.
Without the tithes,
それで祭司たちは畑仕事に
戻ってしまいました
most Levites and singers returned to their fields.
Why have you not returned?
あなたは残ったんですね？
はい あるもので何とかやっています
My lord, I’m getting by.
I’ve always believed that Jehovah helps
エホバは信仰を持つ者を
決してお見捨てになりません
those who trust in him.
エホバが必ず事態を正されるはずです
I know he will correct things in his time.
Did Eliashib not tell the people to bring your provisions?
エルヤシブは 食糧を持ってくるよう
人々に言わなかったのですか
In your absence,
あなたが留守の間 マラキが
エルヤシブと祭司たちに
the prophet Malachi warned him and all the priests.
警告を与えました
But Eliashib—
でもエルヤシブは
He took our storeroom and emptied it of our provisions.
食糧の置かれていたこの部屋を
食堂としてトビヤに使わせています
He gave it to Tobiah to use as a dining hall.
Pedaiah, help us get rid of these things.
ペダヤ 手伝ってください
What are you doing?
何をしている？
エルヤシブ！あなたこそ何をしている
Eliashib!
What have you been doing?
Why have you and the deputy rulers
どうして神の家を
ないがしろにしているのですか
neglected the house of God?
ネヘミヤ
Nehemiah.
You and they,
みんなでこの部屋を清め
全て元に戻しなさい
please cleanse this room
and replace the utensils.
おっしゃる通りに
Yes, my lord.
And gather all the Levites,
全てのレビ族と歌い手たち
代官たちを集めなさい
the singers, and the deputy rulers to me.
I’m assigning them all back to their posts.
みんなを持ち場に戻らせます
Pedaiah, I’m placing you, Shelemiah,
ペダヤ シェレムヤとザドクと一緒に
貯蔵室を見てください
and Zadok in charge of the storerooms.
ハナンが手伝います
Hanan will be your assistant.
It’s your responsibility
兄弟たちに食糧を分けてください
to distribute provisions to your brothers.
ネヘミヤ 待ってください
説明しますから
Nehemiah,
wait-wait a second.
Let me explain this.
これから ユダの人たちに
And I will tell all Judah
to bring in the tenth of the grain,
穀物と新しいぶどう酒と油の
10分の1を持ってくるように伝えます
the new wine, and the oil.
I can explain this.
聞いてください
No, no, wait.
待って
Do remember me, O my God,
エホバ覚えていてください
神の家のために私が示した
揺るぎない愛を
and do not wipe out my acts of loyal love
for the house of my God.
Not only had they neglected Jehovah’s house
エホバの家がないがしろに
されていただけではありません
but some of the Jews
エホバが神聖なものとして
定めた 安息日に
continued to conduct business on the Sabbath
商売をしている人もいました
—a day Jehovah had declared as holy.
今日は何があるの？
What are you selling today?
Only the best quality fish from Tyre.
おいしい魚だ
ティルスのね
What are you doing?
何をしているのですか
今日は安息日です
Do you not care that this is the Sabbath?
ネヘミヤ
Nehemiah.
安息日を汚すとは何事ですか
What is this evil thing you’re doing?
だからこの町は滅ぼされたんです！
That’s why God brought disaster on this city!
今じゃみんなやってます
The people think it’s acceptable now.
What does Jehovah think?
エホバはどう思う
私は商売をやめさせ
I stopped the buying and selling
and ordered the doors closed
安息日を神聖なものとするために
扉を閉じさせました
so as to keep the Sabbath day holy.
But the following week, the merchants tried again.
でも 次の週も
商人たちはやってきました
What’s the meaning of this?
一体どういうつもりだ？
I had to sleep on the ground last night.
昨日は野宿したんだぞ
律法を知ってますよね
You know God’s Law: No work,
安息日には仕事も商売もしてはいけない
no business on the Sabbath!
帰りなさい！安息日を神聖なものと
するために見張ってください
Go!
You and all the Levites, guard the gates
and keep the Sabbath holy.
Don’t let anyone in!
誰も入れてはいけません
This, too, remember to my credit, O my God,
エホバ どうかこのことも覚えていて
and show me pity
私に揺るぎない愛と
思いやりを示してください
according to your abundant loyal love.
問題はほかにもありました
There was another thing that I had to do.
おいで
Come along.
Ana la mitbayen.
Ana la mitbayen
戻ってきなさい！
お父さんの言うことを聞くんだ！
Come back here!
You have to listen to me. I’m your father!
What’s wrong with your children?
どうしたんですか
They don’t like coming to the temple.
神殿に行きたがらないんです
Sweetie, why don’t you like it?
ねえ？どうして嫌なの？
Shvok Y-ati!
待ちなさい！
Come back here now!
すいません 妻が
ヘブライ語を話さないので
I’m sorry, my lord.
My wife speaks very little Hebrew.
あなたは エホバに仕えていない人と
結婚しないと誓いましたね
Did you not swear never to marry someone
who doesn’t serve Jehovah?
ネヘミヤ もう昔の話です
Nehemiah, nobody cares.
Did you not?
何言ってるんだ！
分かった 分かった！
Yes! Yes!
Then why have you ignored the command of Jehovah
なぜ エホバの命令と
自分の誓約を軽んじるのですか
and your own oath?
放してくれ！
Let me go!
No wonder your children don’t love Jehovah.
親がこれじゃ子供はエホバを愛せない
Aah!
エホバの祝福なしに
成功できるとでも思うのか！
Did you imagine that you could succeed
without Jehovah’s blessing?
祝福は祈り求めている！
I prayed for Jehovah’s blessing!
Did you?
そうか！でも神に従っていない
But you didn’t obey him.
Raham, how can Jehovah bless something
ラハム 律法に反する結婚を
エホバが祝福するはずがない
that is against his will?
それはある意味仕方のないことでした
Why was I surprised?
人々を教え導く立場の人たちが
The people were just following
the bad example of those taking the lead.
悪い手本を示していたからです
エルヤシブの孫はベト・ホロンの人と
結婚しています
Eliashib’s grandson married a Horonite,
the daughter of Sanballat.
サンバラテの娘です
どうして律法を不敬に扱うのですか
Have you no respect for God’s Law?
他の民族の娘を
You should not give your daughters to their sons
or accept any of their daughters for your sons
あなたたちの息子や自分のために
迎えてはなりません
or yourselves!
イスラエルの王ソロモンは
そのことで罪を
犯したのではありませんか
Was it not because of these that King Solomon sinned?
何か言ってよ おじいちゃん
Grandfather, say something.
黙っていなさい
Be still, my son.
Is it not something unheard of
他の民族の女性と結婚することなど
for you to commit this great evil
あってはならない神に対する
大きな罪です
by marrying foreign women?
あなたは祭司職を汚しています
You have defiled the priesthood!
祭司を辞めて
エルサレムから出ていきなさい
You may not serve as a priest or remain in Jerusalem.
Fine.
分かった じゃあサマリアに行く
I’ll go to Samaria.
They’re more tolerant there.
ここは窮屈だ
あれは私の孫だ
But he’s my grandson.
Then why did you allow him
ではなぜ 黙って見ていたのですか
to disregard Jehovah’s laws?
神との良い関係を保つには
神殿での奉仕が不可欠です
You know our temple services
are what preserve our relationship with God!
知っていますよね
But as soon as I left,
それなのにあなたたちは
all of you,
私がここにいない間
自分たちがすべきことを
していませんでした
you let it fall apart.
時間はかかりましたが
It took some time, but true worship was restored.
再び真の崇拝が
行われるようになりました
When I look back on all
今思えば エホバはいつも力を
与えてくださいました
that Jehovah enabled us to do
たとえ反対に遭っても・・・
despite the opposition we faced, . . .
I recommend
いい考えがあります
we turn the accusation of sedition
ネヘミヤを反逆の罪で
訴えるのはどうでしょう
against Nehemiah.
The next sound they hear
こうなったら攻め込むしかないだろう
will be our battle cry.
殺されるまで待ってろと言うのですか？
Are you going to wait until they start killing us?
. . . the bad influences we avoided, . . .
良くない影響にさらされても・・・
好きな所に住む権利がある そうだろ
選ばれたら おまえも断るんだ
I have a right to live where I choose, and so do you.
I need you to join me in refusing to move.
お買い得なのに 賢くいこうよ！
そんなの ただの伝統だろ
Don’t waste your money!
Be practical!
Besides, it’s only a tradition.
If we want to eat,
畑や羊の世話をしないと
食べていけないし
we need to go tend our own flocks and fields.
エホバに仕えてる意味が分かんない
It’s of no value to serve God.
. . . the sleepless nights, . . .
眠れない夜も・・・
エルサレムに行こう
ネヘミヤから目を離すな
We must go to Jerusalem to keep an eye on Nehemiah.
やつらは俺たちのやってることが
気に食わないんだ 分からないんですか
Don’t you see? These people hate what we’re doing.
They hate us.
You don’t have to live and work around them like we do.
何も知らないくせに！
. . . the sweat and toil, . . .
仕事がきつくても・・・
Besides, this work is too much for us.
それに仕事が多過ぎる もうへとへとだ
We’re worn out.
そもそも何で城壁が必要なんだ？
Why do we need a wall anyway?
そんな中でも 正しい方法で
エホバに仕えていた私たちは
. . . I just remember the joy we felt
because we were serving Jehovah the right way.
喜びに満たされていました
We thought we were just working on a wall,
私たちはただ城壁を建て直している
と思っていましたが
エホバは私たちの信仰を
建て直してくださっていたのです
but Jehovah was rebuilding our faith.
エホバがご自分の目的を
成し遂げるために
I’ll never forget how Jehovah
私たちを集めてくださったことを
brought us together to accomplish his will.
私は決して忘れないでしょう
He taught us to rely on him,
エホバは ご自分に頼るよう
私たちを教え 強めてくださったのです
and he strengthened us.
良い物を食べ ぶどう酒を飲み
Eat the choice things, and drink what is sweet,
持っていない人と分け合いましょう
and send a portion to those who have nothing.
And do not feel sad,
悲しんではいけません
for the joy of Jehovah is your stronghold.
エホバからの喜びは
皆さんの力となるのです
私の神 私のことをどうか覚えていて
Do remember me favorably, O my God.
恵みを与えてくださいますように
Nehemiah was a man of courage.
ネヘミヤには勇気がありました
He could have stayed in the luxurious palace
快適なシュシャンの宮殿にとどまり
of Shushan and served Jehovah from there.
そこでエホバに仕えることも
できましたが
そうはしませんでした
But he didn’t.
When a need arose,
必要が生じた時
兄弟たちを助けるために
he was ready to make the long journey
エルサレムへの長旅をすることを
いといませんでした
to Jerusalem to support his brothers.
But it wouldn’t be easy.
でもそれは簡単ではありません
First, he had to ask the king of Persia to let him go.
まず ペルシャの王の許可が必要でした
What helped Nehemiah
ネヘミヤが勇気を出して王に話すのに
何が助けになったでしょうか
to be a courageous person for Jehovah?
Did he rely on his personality
自分の能力や王との
良い関係に頼ったでしょうか
or his good record with the king?
この部分をもう一度見てみましょう
Let’s watch this part again.
The place where my forefathers are buried lies in ruins,
エルサレムが荒れ果て 門も焼け落ちて
しまっていると聞いたので・・・
and its gates have been consumed by fire.
そうだったのか・・・
Nehemiah, what is this?
Speak frankly.
それでおまえはどうしたいと
思っているんだ？
What are you seeking?
At once, I prayed to the God of the heavens.
すぐに天の父に祈りました
もし私が
If it pleases the king
and if your servant has found favor with you,
王の好意を得ており
send me to Judah,
王が良いと思われるのでしたら
to the city where my forefathers are buried,
私をユダに行かせ
そこを再建させてください
and let me rebuild it.
You may go.
行きなさい
Jehovah was with us.
エホバは祈りに答えてくださいました
Nehemiah immediately and humbly prayed to Jehovah,
ネヘミヤは すぐにそして謙遜に
勇気を下さる方エホバに祈りました
the true Source of courage.
In fact, he prayed repeatedly
その後も繰り返し祈りつつ働き
throughout his assignment,
エホバはその努力を祝福されました
and Jehovah blessed his efforts.
それで最初の教訓です
So lesson number one for us today:
私たちは 苦しい時には
エホバに頼るかもしれません
When times are hard,
we may be quick to lean on Jehovah.
でも問題が何もない時はどうですか
But what if things are going well?
そのような時にも
エホバに頼るでしょうか
Are we still reliant on Jehovah?
Or might we find ourselves
こんなふうに考えるかもしれません
becoming complacent, perhaps even saying:
「自分は今の生活に満足している
“Things are good in my life now.
これまで長年エホバにお仕えしてきた
“I know there’s a need to get to work,
やるべきことがたくさんあるのは
分かっているけど
“but I’ve been serving Jehovah for many years now.
自分の分は十分果たした
“I’ve done my part.
後はほかの人にやってもらおう」
Let someone else do it”?
Will Jehovah bless such an attitude?
エホバはこのような態度を
喜ばれるでしょうか
Wouldn’t it be better to turn to Jehovah in prayer,
「もっと奉仕を続けることができるよう
勇気と喜びを与えてください」と
asking him to give you the courage and joy
エホバに祈り求める方が
良いのではないでしょうか
to continue to reach out in your service to him?
You just might be surprised
きっとエホバは 思いも寄らない
奉仕の機会を開いてくださるでしょう
at the doors Jehovah opens for you.
さて エルサレムに到着したネヘミヤは
Now, once Nehemiah arrived in Jerusalem,
he didn’t just give orders, did he?
人々に指示を出すだけでは
ありませんでした
The Bible says that he daily worked
聖書によれば ネヘミヤは毎日
alongside his fellow Israelites
「夜明けから星が出る頃まで」
“from the break of dawn
until the stars came out.”
仲間のイスラエル人たちと
一緒に働きました
In a similar way,
私たちが同じように
自己犠牲の精神を示す時
when we show a self-sacrificing spirit,
Jehovah will give us the energy needed
エホバは私たちにも
必要な力を与えてくださいます
to carry out the task at hand.
The Israelites completed
イスラエル人は わずか52日で
城壁を完成させました
the wall-building project in just 52 days!
What an amazing feat,
さまざまな反対の中での再建工事は
especially in the face of continual opposition!
まさに偉業と言えます
反対者たちは最初
あざけるだけでしたが
At first, it came in the form of mocking.
やがて実力行使に出ると言って
脅してきます
Then the opposers threatened to attack!
There were Samaritans in the north,
当時のエルサレムは 北にサマリア人
Ammonites in the east, Arabs in the south,
東にアンモン人 南にアラビア人
and Ashdodites in the west.
そして西にアシュドドの人たちと
Jerusalem was surrounded by enemies.
敵に囲まれていました
八方ふさがりと思える状況でした
It could have been easy to feel trapped
and to give in to fear.
What did Nehemiah do?
この局面でネヘミヤはどうしましたか
Well, what was his pattern?
In his own words, he says:
やはり「神に祈り」ました
“We prayed to our God.”
そして 「彼らのことを
恐れてはなりません
Then Nehemiah strengthened the people
偉大で威厳に満ちる
エホバがおられることを
by telling them:
“Do not be afraid of them.
忘れないでください」と言って
皆を励ましました
Remember Jehovah, who is great and awe-inspiring.”
城壁再建の作業が
止まることはありませんでした
And so they kept building.
After Nehemiah’s enemies
敵たちは 自分たちの脅しが
効かなかったことを知って
realized that their open threats had failed,
引き下がりましたか
did they give up?
いいえ 別の手を使いました
No.
They now turned to other forms of opposition.
ネヘミヤに城壁の再建をやめさせるため
In fact, they tried three different schemes
3つの巧妙なわなを仕掛けました
to sidetrack Nehemiah from the work.
覚えておられますか？
Did you notice them?
Let’s watch the video again.
ビデオを見てみましょう
まず ネヘミヤを町の外に
おびき出そうとしました
They asked to meet Nehemiah halfway.
Tell this to Nehemiah:
ネヘミヤにこう伝えろ
「オノの谷あいの平原の村で会おう」
“Come,
“and let us set a time to meet together
in the Valley Plain of Ono.”
They’re trying to lure me away
私をエルサレムからおびき出すつもりだ
from Jerusalem to do me harm.
次に 根も葉もないうわさを流しました
They spread false rumors.
ゲシェム あの手で行くしかないな
Geshem, it’s time to implement your plan.
Tobiah, write this down:
トビヤ 書いてくれ
“Among the nations it has been heard,
「周りの民族の間で
あなたのことがうわさになっている
“and Geshem is also saying it,
ゲシェムも言っていたが
“that you and the Jews
あなたとユダヤ人は
反逆をもくろんでいる
“are scheming to rebel.
That is why you are building the wall.”
だから城壁を建て直している」
And they used a traitor to try and trick Nehemiah.
そして 裏切り者を使ってネヘミヤを
わなにはめようとしました
They’re coming to kill you—by night!
やつらが殺しに来る 今夜だ！
We must go into the temple
神殿に逃げ込んで 扉を閉めるんだ
and close the doors.
Shemaiah,
シェマヤ 総督である私が逃げるのか？
should a man like me run away?
そんなこと言ってる場合じゃない
You don’t understand.
いや 私がそんなことをしたら
みんなはどう思う？
What would that do to the spirit of the entire nation?
安全な場所はそこしかない
It’s the only safe place.
それに 私は祭司でもない
Besides, I’m not a priest.
If I entered the temple,
神殿に入ることは許されていない
that would be valid reason to kill me.
I will not go in.
私は入らない！
That decision would be foolish, Nehemiah.
俺の言う通りにするんだ
Oh, I see!
そうか
Tobiah and Sanballat put you up to this,
トビヤとサンバラテの差し金か
didn’t they, you hypocrite?
この裏切者！
エホバは 敵たちと あなた方
偽預言者たちを処罰される
May Jehovah remember them
and all of you false prophets
who keep trying to frighten me.
Come, Hanani,
行こうハナニ 仕事に戻ろう
we have work to do.
Three schemes, three failures
敵は 3回わなを仕組みましたが
3回とも失敗します
—so lesson number two:
Like Nehemiah, we might encounter opposers
ここから2つ目の教訓が得られます
私たちも ネヘミヤのように
who scheme to bring our loyal service to a halt.
敵たちからの妨害を受けるでしょう
Some may invite us to meet them halfway, so to speak.
その1つは 私たちを
妥協させようとするわなです
They may try to convince us that if we serve Jehovah
例えば エホバへの奉仕の手を
少し緩めれば
with just a little less zeal,
we could pursue
この世界で成功できると言う人がいます
worldly goals at the same time.
しかし私たちは 神の王国を
第一にした生活をしているので
However, because God’s Kingdom
comes first in our lives,
we can be like Nehemiah and refuse to compromise.
妥協はしません
この世界がどこに向かっているかを
知っているからです
We know where this world is headed.
また敵たちは 根も葉もない
うわさを広めます
Opposers also spread false accusations against us.
In some lands, we’re accused
ある国では 私たちが国家を脅かす
存在だと非難されています
of posing a threat to the State.
Some accusations have been successfully
裁判で私たちが勝訴した例もありますが
rebutted in court.
But whatever the outcome,
どんな結果になるとしても
we’re confident that Jehovah will direct matters
エホバが物事を導いてくださることを
確信できます
according to his will.
Opposition may also come from those
そして エホバに仕えているふりをする
人たちからの攻撃もあります
who pretend to serve Jehovah.
命を守るため ネヘミヤに神の律法を
破るよう唆したユダヤ人がいたように
Just as a fellow Jew tried to get Nehemiah
to break God’s Law to save his life,
so former Witnesses may try
偽兄弟たちは 私たちが
何かの点で妥協するよう
to get us to compromise in one way or another.
わなを仕組んでくるかもしれません
それでも 命が救われるためには
However, we reject apostates because we know
神の律法を破るのではなく
that our lives are saved,
それを守る必要があることを
私たちは知っているので
not by breaking God’s laws, but by keeping them.
そのような背教者たちを退けます
Each time, Nehemiah refused to fall into their trap.
結局 ネヘミヤはわなに
はまりませんでした
Why?
なぜでしょうか
Because he had a brilliant mind?
頭が良かったからでしょうか
No!
It was because he relied on Jehovah,
そういうことではありません
いつもエホバに頼ったので
and Jehovah gave him the insight needed
エホバが彼に敵の策略を見抜く
洞察力をお与えになったのです
to see through their deceptions.
After the wall was built,
城壁再建の後
Nehemiah left Jerusalem for a while.
ネヘミヤはしばらくの間
エルサレムを離れました
But what did he find on his return?
戻ってきた時 そこは
どうなっていましたか
Instead of coming back to find true worship thriving,
真の崇拝は 嘆かわしい
状態にありました
he found it barely surviving.
All the work that he had done
これまで すでに一生懸命
働いてきたネヘミヤは
to help the people to trust in Jehovah
どのように考えましたか
—how do you think he felt?
「私はもう十分にやった
He could have said: “That’s it!
後は 誰かに任せよう」と言って
投げ出すこともできたでしょう
“I’m out!
Let someone else clean this up,” and walked away.
でも そうはしませんでした
But did he?
見てみましょう
Let’s watch again.
Why have you and the deputy rulers
どうして神の家を
ないがしろにしているのですか
neglected the house of God?
みんなでこの部屋を清め
全て元に戻しなさい
You and they, please cleanse this room.
You know God’s Law:
律法を知ってますよね
No work, no business
安息日には仕事も商売もしてはいけない
on the Sabbath!
Go!
帰りなさい！
Did you not swear never to marry someone
あなたは エホバに仕えていない人と
結婚しないと誓いましたね
who doesn’t serve Jehovah?
Then why have you ignored the command of Jehovah
なぜ エホバの命令と
自分の誓約を軽んじるのですか
and your own oath?
Also, Eliashib’s grandson married a Horonite,
エルヤシブの孫は
ベト・ホロンの人と結婚しています
the daughter of Sanballat.
サンバラテの娘です
他の民族の娘をあなたたちの息子や
自分のために迎えてはなりません
You should not give your daughters to their sons
or accept any of their daughters for your sons!
あなたは祭司職を汚しています
You have defiled the priesthood!
You may not serve as a priest
祭司を辞めて
エルサレムから出ていきなさい
or remain in Jerusalem.
It took some time
時間はかかりましたが
but true worship was restored.
再び真の崇拝が
行われるようになりました
Nehemiah didn’t walk away, did he?
ネヘミヤは最後までやり抜きました
No, he persevered in his assignment.
なぜそうできたのでしょうか
Why?
Because he held on to his joy.
喜びがあったからです
You see, his main source of joy came,
ネヘミヤの喜びの一番の理由は
not from his accomplishments,
城壁を完成させたという達成感でも
not from the security of walls,
城壁があるという安心感でも
or even from what others were doing.
ほかの人の行動でもありませんでした
From where does true joy come?
ネヘミヤ自身こう述べています
Nehemiah himself told us:
「エホバからの喜びは
皆さんの力となるのです」
“The joy of Jehovah is your stronghold.”
So here is lesson number three for us:
それで 3つ目の教訓です
Despite challenges and setbacks,
どんな試練や障害があっても
we can be joyful because true joy comes
喜びの一番の理由は
エホバとの良い関係にあるので
from a good relationship with Jehovah.
私たちは幸せでいられます
Nehemiah was a man like you and me.
ネヘミヤは私たちと同じ
不完全な人間です
Remember, he didn’t have Jehovah’s power
また モーセやヨシュアが見たような
奇跡を見ることもありませんでした
displayed supernaturally to him
like Moses and Joshua did.
では ネヘミヤが成功したのは
どうしてですか
But what did he have?
He had prayer, he had faith,
エホバに祈り エホバを信じ
and he had trust.
エホバに頼ったからです
Those were his tools.
そして エホバご自身が
ネヘミヤのために行動し
And there is no doubt that Jehovah
その努力を導き 祝福されたことに
疑問の余地はありません
was active on behalf of Nehemiah,
guiding and blessing his efforts.
終わりの日に住む私たちも同じです
We have those same tools today.
エホバに祈り エホバを信じ
Pray to Jehovah, put faith in him,
エホバに頼りましょう
and trust that he will bless your self-sacrificing efforts.
エホバは必ず祝福してくださいます
Just as Jehovah gave Nehemiah
ネヘミヤに 勇気 力 洞察力
the courage, the energy, the insight,
and the perseverance to carry out his assignment,
粘り強さを与えたエホバは
あなたのことも必ず
支えてくださるでしょう
he’ll do the same for you.